Hello friends, best wishes to all of you for this Hindu New
Year, Nav Samvatsara
and also best wishes to all of you for this holy festival of Cheti Chand and Eid.
So friends, today's video of mine is basically
defining the
benefits of health insurance or
what are the rules of the health insurance company, what
things are covered in it,
everyone wanted to know whether one should
take health insurance or not, should one take it
for the family, should one take it alone
or I am still very young, what will I do by
taking it, so there were many such doubts,
covering all those things, what is basically
health insurance, what things does it
provide us, so today I am going to
explain to you about the same, basically there are
two types of things in health insurance,
one cashless and one non-
cashless, cashless system is that
whichever company we have taken our health insurance
policy from, which we have purchased,
after a particular time period, their
waiting period is at least minimum 30
days or day law, which  Every company has a
waiting period of 30 days
in its new policy. If it is a case of port, then the
waiting period depends on the time shot and it
works on how many days it will be.
So what will happen in cashless is that
if the
company has a tie-up with the hospital where we are taking treatment, then whatever
claim will be there, the hospital will directly
claim it from its company and if it does
not have a tie-up, then it will be called non-cashless,
for which we will have to
pay the hospital in advance and after
discharge, whatever our original bills,
reports, tests,
we will have to provide all those things to our company
in the form of original soft copy. If it is
called soft copy, then that or
whatever hard copy is demanded, the company has to
submit it. The second thing
which is most important for us is what things are
covered and what are not covered.
In health insurance, basically the
first option is that any disease related to AIDS or HIV, the
health insurance
company will not cover it. Any
disease related to HIV or AIDS,
no company will cover it.  Dental treatment will not be covered.
Dental treatment is the most important thing
which basically no health
insurance company used to cover till now but
according to the new features coming, there are a few companies
which have given a particular limit in which
a small amount is
covered for dental treatment. Otherwise, in
case of any accidental dental problem, then
every company covers all those things.
Secondly, our thing is
that cosmetic surgery, generally many times if the
fat increases a lot or
we have to get any kind of
cosmetic surgery done on the face, then no
company covers that also. In case of maternity, there are
some selected plans of a few companies in
which there is a
particular waiting period.
After that waiting period, that maternity
cover is also provided. Very few companies
cover maternity.
Intoxication means if someone has a habit of drinking
or does any other type of intoxicant and
due to that some disease occurs or those
things have to be removed. Many people get rid of alcohol to get rid of alcohol.
No health insurance company covers the different types of treatments that you get done. Thirdly,
our capping is that in some companies there is
capping on many things like I have to pay
1 percent of the room rent or I will pay this much for ICU expenses
and there are some companies which
basically cover whatever the room cost as per your bills and whatever the
ICU expenses are, whatever the
actual things are, it depends
on different companies, their plans, the
company covers them according to their terms and conditions.
Fourth point is our geographical
zone, some companies work in a particular zone,
like today in metro
cities, the health treatments are
different there or if you go to a small place or a
rural area, the treatment
process is different there, the charges, accommodation, food,
everything is different, so it depends
that some companies
demand premium from you according to their geography, some of the premiums are
absolutely single for all across India, the
premium will be the same for everyone, no matter where you are, or what kind of
treatment you are getting done.  It will be the same for them.
Next is payment to no.
What is co-payment? Generally, suppose
you will pay some percentage of your expenses
directly and the company will pay some. So
these are co-payment options. So
basically, what I explained to you here in this video,
what are the things in health insurance, cashless and non-
cashless are two main things. Other things are what
IRDA says about what it
covers and what it does not cover, which
diseases it does not cover. I explained that
thirdly, what is capping?
If there is any room rent, the
company decides how much charges will be there according to that.
Some companies pay the entire amount,
some impose capping charges. Second,
our fourth point was about the
geographical region, in which state
or which place is he getting his treatment,
where is he staying, the
premium will be according to that. And fifthly, our point was
no. payments, what are co-payments,
what kind of charges will there be,
some percentage will be waived by the company, you will have to pay some.
So, there are
basic things in health insurance, which are the basic things
that I have shared with you and
any plan is purchased according to this.
Secondly, if
someone has a history of any old disease or many other things,
we do not ask about them, some are due to family genes,
we should always explain them, so
these are the benefits of health insurance,
everyone should take it, ADAC
Ergo, ICICI, Lord Niva Bhupa and
apart from this, all the health insurance companies have
very good plans, I would suggest
you, HDFC's services are very good,
ICICI's services are also very good,
we also work with Niva Bhupa, so
basically there are many companies with whom we
work, so you can
meet me for whichever plan you want according to your needs,
thank you friends, I have mentioned my number
here and
you can call me for more information, thank you.